<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the thirtie day of May. 1591 By M. George Giffard, preacher of the worde of God at Maldon in Essex.</title>
            <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11862.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898868</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898868</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150926</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72180)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1988:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the thirtie day of May. 1591 By M. George Giffard, preacher of the worde of God at Maldon in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by I. Windet for Tobie Cooke, at the Tigers head in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reprinted in STC 11848.5--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse of the 133. Psal.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on A3r: Psalme. 133. Beholde how good and how, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Peterborough Cathedral, Peterborough, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXXIII --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150926:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Pauls Croſſe the thirtie day of May. 1591. By M. George Gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fard, <hi>Preacher of the</hi> worde of God at <hi>Maldon in Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by I. Windet for <hi>Tobie Cooke, at the Tigers head</hi> in Paules Churchyard. 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150926:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150926:2"/>
            <head>To the worſhipfull, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter William Rider, Alderman, and elect Sheriefe of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, this Sermon was preached at Paules Croſſe the <hi>30.</hi> of Maye laſte, at the which ther were ſome that gathered the ſame in writing ſo neere as they could, their coppies being conferred and laid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, were (neuertheleſse) found very imperfect, ſo that the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher was requeſted to perfecte the ſame ſo neere as his memorie would
<pb facs="tcp:150926:3"/> ſuffer him, the which hauing doone and the coppie comminge to my handes, J haue by publicke autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie printed it, I hope to the good of manie. And findinge my ſelfe greatlie indebted to your worſhippe and yours for many curteſies, J was bolde to preſent it vnto you as a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of my thankeful minde, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that you will accept the ſame in as good part as I meant it. And ſo beſeechinge God to bleſſe your worſhippe to the fulfillinge of that hope which many conceiue of you in time to come, I humblye take my leaue this 7. of Auguſt. <hi>1591.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips humbly affectionate to commaund. T. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:150926:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalme. 133.</bibl>
                  <p>Beholde how good and how, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Prophet, King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was the compoſer and writer of this Pſalme, as the Title thereof dooth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly mention.</p>
            <p>It is called a ſonge of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées, as there bee 14. other beſides this, here ſet together of the ſame title, but in what ſence: the learned interpreters are of diuers iudgementes. I will followe that which is moſt probable by the holy Scriptures. The word <hi>Magnaloth,</hi> which the Prophet heere vſeth, dooth properlie ſignifie ſteps or ſtaires, by which we aſſend into higher places. But by <hi>Metaphor</hi> (as I take it to be here vſed) it ſignifieth high eſtate, high degrée, excellencie, or dignitie. For proofe heereof wee reade. 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 17. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. where <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaking vnto God, ſayth, thou haſt regarded me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the eſtate of a man of high degrée, vſing the ſame worde that is here. So then,
<pb facs="tcp:150926:4"/> if wee conſider the phraſe of the Hebrewe tongue, which to expreſſe the ſuperlatiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée, vſeth the plurall number, a ſong of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées, that is, a ſong of excellencies, or a ſong of dignities, is as much as to ſay, a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, or a moſt worthy ſong. The holy ghoſt in giuing this title, dooth, as it were, ſet a marke in the forehead of the Pſalme, to giue notice vnto vs, that there is a treaſure of moſt excellent doctrine, &amp; moſt fitte for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction contained in it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may with the greater diligence &amp; attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue eare vnto it.</p>
            <p>The Argument or the matter here hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is all but one. For the holy ghoſt with a very high and ſinguler praiſe, through the whole Pſalme dooth ſeth foorth and commend the vnitie and concord of brethren. The bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (which he ſpeaketh of and which are to kéepe this holie agréement) are all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children of the Church, fellow members of Chriſtes miſticall body, and true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God, among whom is the ſpirituall brother-hoode. The vertue it ſelfe which is here commended, is that ſame which S. <hi>Paul</hi> dooth ſo earneſtlye exhorte and perſwade all Chriſtian men vnto, to kéepe the vnity of the ſpirite, in the bonde of peace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. The Primitiue Church is commended for
<pb facs="tcp:150926:4"/> the practiſe thereof, in which wee haue a liuely example ſet before vs: for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that the multitude of them that belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued were of one hart, and of one ſoule, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 32. For as one body conſiſting of many members, hath but one hart and one ſoule, by which all the members are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited, and loue each other, ſo the multitude were vnited in iudgement and affection, as if there were but one hart and one ſoule in them all.</p>
            <p>The commendation and praiſe by which the holy ghoſt ſetteth foorth the excellent worthines of this vertue, is vnder two E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithites, which are theſe, good and comelie. For he ſaith, beholde howe good and howe comely a thing it is, for brethren alſo to dwell in vnitie. Theſe two Epithites hee afterward openeth and amplifieth by two ſimilitudes: the one is taken from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of <hi>Aaron</hi> with the precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to declare chéefelye the ſwéete and pleaſant comelines of this vnitie: the other is taken from the dewe of <hi>Hermon,</hi> which commeth downe vpon the mountaines of <hi>Sion,</hi> to expreſſe the fruit and good that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thereof. And finallie hee concludeth from the higheſt cauſe, euen the Lord God,
<pb facs="tcp:150926:5"/> who hath commaunded the bleſſing of life eternall to bee vpon this vnitie. This is bréefelie the ſumme of the Pſalme, or of this praiſe which is giuen. Now come to to the expoſition.</p>
            <p>By the firſt word (behold) the Prophete dooth ſtirre vp the minds of the Iſraelites, euen of all the Tribes, to take viewe how bleſſed a thing vnity and concorde is, euen by their owne experience which they had, partlie by the former times, and partlie by the time then preſent. For in former daies they had felt with much ſorrow, the great calamities, harmes, and annoyaunces of diſcorde: &amp; at this time now preſent when this Pſalme was giuen, they ſaw the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and benefites of vnity and peace. For their former experience in the dayes of King <hi>Saule,</hi> when hee perſecuted <hi>Dauid</hi> which had done none euill, the worſhip of God was neglected, good men were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, euill men floriſhed, with much gréefe of minde vnto many, then was there diſcord, ſo far as men durſt ſpeake. When <hi>Saule</hi> was taken away, and <hi>Dauid</hi> was annointed King in <hi>Hebron, Abner</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ner</hi> Captaine of <hi>Saules</hi> armie, tooke <hi>Iſhboſheth Saules</hi> ſonne, and ſette
<pb facs="tcp:150926:5"/> him vp for King, the diſcorde then grewe much greater, for then one part of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes claue vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> the other vnto the houſe of <hi>Saule.</hi> They were indéede all the ſonnes of <hi>Iaacob</hi> and profeſſed the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whome they ſhould with one mouth haue worſhipped and glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. but they were deuided and rent a ſunder, for there was bloudy warre and long time continued among the Tribes: 2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 3. brethren with deadly hatred and enmitie purſuing their brethren, ſéeking the bloud eache of other. It could not bee but that great calamities in this time of diſcord did ouerſpred the whole land: they might by experience then and did beholde how euill and how miſchéeuous a thing it is, for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to be at variance. The cutting down of ſo great an euill, and taking away all occaſion is a verye great good. Therefore when <hi>Abner</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſheboſheth</hi> were ſlaine, all Iſraell came togeather and ſet vp <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi> Then there grewe a reconciliation of Tribe vnto Tribe, and they which were before rente a ſunder, became againe one body, brethren imbraced eache other with loue, the bitter hatred before among them
<pb facs="tcp:150926:6"/> was cutte downe and extinguiſhed. The worſhip of God was now ſet vp, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges of God were powred downe from heauen vpon them in great plentye, the whole land did reioyce with ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: Therfore he willeth them now to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how good and howe comelie a thing it is, for brethren to dwell alſo at vnitie. Thus were they taught by their owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience on both ſides: For they had found the gréeuous annoyances of diſcorde, and enmity on the one part, and the benefite of peace on the other, and this is it he willeth them to behold. Behold how good and how comelie a thing it is, which dooth cutte downe ſo great euill, and behold how good and how comelie a thing it is, which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with it ſuch great bleſſinges of God: thus much for the firſt word. Then to the praiſe it ſelfe: the firſt Epithite is (howe good) which containeth the great fruit that ariſeth thereof, and is afterward ſet forth by the ſeconde compariſon, that is, of the the dewe of <hi>Hermon:</hi> for that is a thing fruitefull and good. The other is (how comelie) the word is <hi>Magnim,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth beautifull, ſwéete, comelie, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt: as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. Where he ſpeaketh of
<pb facs="tcp:150926:6"/> the reſurrection and exaltation of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, ſaying. Thou wilte ſhewe me the path of life, the fulnes of ioye is in thy preſence, at thy right hande comely pleaſures for euermore. This comelie plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſwéetnes of concord, is reſembled and ſhadowed foorth by the former ſimilitude, that is, of <hi>Aarons</hi> annointing, for that was a verie comelie and a ſwéet thing, and had a miſticall ſignification. To vnderſtande the better what is here meant, firſt ye may reade of this precious oyntment, both whereof the Lord commaunded it ſhoulde be made, and how <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sonnes ſhould bee annointed therewith vnto the préeſts office, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. Then further we are taught in the Scriptures, that <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> was a figure of Chriſt, and that this anointing of his with that precious ſwéet oyntment, did repreſent the ſpirituall and heauenly annoynting of Chriſt Ieſus with the holy Ghoſt, whoſe graces diſtill fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the head, vpon euery parte of his miſticall bodie, which is the Church. Of him it is ſayd, the ſpirite of the Lorde is vpon mee, becauſe he hath annointed me, &amp;c. <hi>Luke.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. Marke further then wherein the compariſon holdeth. Thus powringe the
<pb facs="tcp:150926:7"/> precious oyntment vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Aarons</hi> head, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his heard, and to the ſcirts of his clothing, was pleaſant to behold, and caſt forth a ſwéete ſauor vnto all that ſtood round about. Alſo in that it diſcendeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his beard, and ſo downeward vpon all parts euen to the ſcirtes of his clothing, it reſembleth the graces of the holye Ghoſt flowing downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, vpon all the members of his body knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in an holy vnity. When it went downe from <hi>Aarons</hi> head vpon his body vnited to the ſame, it diſcendeth euen to the loweſt part of his garmente, becauſe there is no rent nor ſeperation. Euen ſo the Church vnited vnto Chriſt, her head, &amp; euery member of the ſame vnited vnto the reſt in an holie vnion, and making one bodie, the heauenly graces of the holie Ghoſt, farre ſwéeter then that precious oyntment, flowe from him vpon them, and all are partakers thereof, euen the loweſt and meaneſt member, euen to the ſcirtes. For where they are ioyned in this ſpirituall vnitie, looke what gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſoeuer God from his Sonne Chriſt dooth power vpon the higheſt members, (that is vpon Princes and Paſtors)
<pb facs="tcp:150926:7"/> they diſtill alſo vpon the other parts and members, and ſo from each to other.</p>
            <p>That which was ſeperate from the heade, from the bodie, and from the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of <hi>Aaron,</hi> receiued no droppe of that precious oyntment, which diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the head to a bodie vnited, and to all partes of the garmentes wrought togeather. In like manner the graces of the holy Ghoſt diſcende from Chriſt the heade, vppon nothing that is ſeperate and deuided and rente from him, but vppon all the members vnited in one bodie. Wee may then briefelie ſet foorth what this ſimilitude declareth, in this wiſe. The ſwéete oyntmente is powred vpon the head of <hi>Aaron,</hi> it goeth down vpon his beard, then vpon his ſhoulders and all partes of his bodie euen to the loweſt border of his garmentes. Ieſus Chriſt the heade of the Church is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted with the holy Ghoſt, and from him the ſwéete graces diſcend, and come vpon all the bodie, and vpon euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the bodie euen to the meaneſt: this it is to be vnited to him, and to his Church: this is a thing moſt ſwéete and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150926:8"/>
            <p>In the other ſimilitude hee reſembleth this vnity vnto the dew of <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which commeth downe vpon the Mountaines of <hi>Sion:</hi> the waters which fall vpon the high mountaine diſtill into the valleies, but into thoſe valleies which are ioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto at the foote thereof, and make them plentiouſly fruitfull: euen ſo the heauenly ſpirituall dewes that come downe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue vpon the Mountaines, flowe vpon the vallies which are vnited therunto, and there is great fruite, and all good thinges ſpringing from thence. Thus much wee may conſider in theſe ſimilitudes, which expreſſe how good and how comely a thing it is for brethren alſo to dwell at vnitie.</p>
            <p>Now al this is from the moſt high God, for he ſaith (there) that is to ſay, vpon thoſe which dwell together in this holy vnitie, the Lord hath commaunded the bleſſinge, and life for euermore. It is Gods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable decrée that they ſhall haue the bleſſing, that is, the great great high bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, euen the bleſſing of all bleſſinges in euerlaſting continuance. This can neuer faile, for God almightie is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and what he hath decreede and commaunded, ſhall ſtande for euer. This
<pb facs="tcp:150926:8"/> may perſwade much to dwell in vnitie: for it is a goodly matter to bee vnder the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of almighty God: and there, that is, vpon the vnity of brethren, hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his bleſſing, and no where elſe: for this, there, is as much as to ſay, there only. Now we ſee the praiſe it ſelfe of vnity and concorde here ſet foorth, vnto vs it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that wee conſider to what ende and purpoſe the holye Ghoſt giueth this great commendation. This we all knowe, that when a thing is diſpraiſed, it is to bring vs into a miſliking and ſhunning of the ſame, as a thing either vnpleaſant or hurtfull. And contrariwiſe, praiſe, eſpecially where it is giuen by God, who knoweth the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of euery thing, is to drawe our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and to make vs in loue with that which is praiſed. This is then done heare, that we may haue our harts inflamed, and that we may bee in loue with vnitie and concorde: and that wee maye ſtudiouſlie ſéeke after it, and imbrace it, as a moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious iewell: and finallye by all meanes take héede, that we do not any thing which may hinder and diſturbe the ſame. And doubtleſſe if this can not mooue vs, and kindle an earneſt loue and zeale to be ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
<pb facs="tcp:150926:9"/> of Godly peace, that it is ſo good, ſo ſweete, and pleaſant, and that Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is vpon it vnto eternall life, how dull are we vnto ſpirituall &amp; heauenly thinges, or what can mooue vs? Shall we not care to haue that cutte downe which bringeth miſchiefe and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to ſet vp that which carieth all bleſſednes with it? Shall we neither care to auoide the curſe of God, plagues and puniſhments on the one ſide: nor yet couet to haue his bleſſing, that it may mooue vs the rather, I wil come now to the application of this Pſalme to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            <p>Wee haue (as yee all knowe) receiued great bleſſinges from the Lorde our God, by the meanes of our gracious Quéene. For by her happie raigne, we haue inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long peace, euen ſuch as the like hath not almoſt béene ſéene or heard of in this land. Wee haue alſo great plentie of all thinges, our countrie ouer flowinge with milke and honey: euery man ſitting vnder his Vine and vnder his figge trée. And moreour the Lord hath protected vs by her Scepter and power, from the inuaſion of forraine enemies, and from the wicked practiſes and treaſons of domeſtical aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,
<pb facs="tcp:150926:9"/> theſe are great benefites recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But the greateſt bleſſing of all is, that by her gouernement, hee hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vs from the bondage of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah,</hi> from the heauy yoake of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, out of Idolatrie and blindneſſe, and hath reſtored vnto vs his holie word, and his true worſhip. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there hath béene among vs, many yeeres (as ye all know) great diſcorde and variaunce, and that not onely againſt Papiſtes and other ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the holie religion, but euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong brethren, which profeſſe the ſame holy doctrine and faith of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. An all this time wee haue taſted the bitter fruites of enmitie and diſcorde, we haue felt and ſuſtained the miſchéefes, harmes and dammages that growe from it, ſo that we haue had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience with the Iſralites in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer part, and can ſay of our own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, behold how euill and howe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comelie a thing it is for brethren to be at variaunce. To make this more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, if I ſhould ſtande to rippe vp, and to laye open all the euilles which haue alreadie come vpon vs by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of brethren, it would bee a long
<pb facs="tcp:150926:10"/> and a tedious labour. I will therefore onely note ſome of the cheefe and moſt generall, that beholding as it were our moſt gréeuous woundes, we may ſéeke to haue them ſalued and cured if it may pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I may note as a principall euill fruite of enmity, that it is a ioy, and on ancouragement vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the enemies of the Goſpell, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts for to ſée brethren ſet againſt bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: for as it is in an armie of men, if they be at deadly variance among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, Captaine againſt Captaine, band againſt band, purſuing ech other: That the aduerſe part (againſt which they ſhould wholy together bend their forces) will ſay, wee ſhall not néede to doo much, we ſhall eaſilie preuaile, for they will pull down and deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with their own hands, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will much reioyce. So is it in Gods Church, Chriſtes armie, which is ſet vpon by deadly enemies on euery ſide, when there is diſcorde growing vnto ſharpe enmitie, and the leaders them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bent one part againſt an other, the wicked enemie dooth laugh, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth boldnes and ſtrength, for hee
<pb facs="tcp:150926:10"/> ſaith in his hart, this ſharpe contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amonge them, will procéede in the ende euen vnto blood, and to the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of both partes. O howe much ought we to be pricked and gréeued at the reioycing and boldning of Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies? And how dolefull a calamitie were this, if it ſhould among brethren come vnto blood? We ſee that amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the children of Iſraell, the diſcorde and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie brake foorth euen vnto bloud, and ſo doubtles, excepte the Lord in great mercie turne it away (ſuch is the nature of contention when it groweth ſharpe) that the end among vs alſo wil be moſt gréeuous. This one euill ought to mooue vs to loue and imbrace the holy vnitye heere commended in this Pſalme. I would the conſideration of it might bee deepely printed in our mindes. The wounding of the weake is an other great euil that ariſeth from diſcord: doubtles many are caſt down, or turned out of the way, or at the leaſt much hindred hereby in our Church. Stumbling blockes being thus laide, before the blinde and lame. What pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie this ought to mooue, and how much the ſight of it ſhould vexe and gréeue
<pb facs="tcp:150926:11"/> vs, the doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt vttered by him ſelfe and by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dooth euerie where ſhew: threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges alſo and woes are pronounced againſt them, that ſhall caſt downe the weake: And ſhall not we regarde this thing at all: ſhall neither the compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and loue to our brethren for whome Chriſt died, nor the threatninges and woes denounced take any place? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the diſcord of brethren, dooth bring both parts into contempt and diſgrace among many. And ſo by this meanes the miniſters of the Goſpell, the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Chriſt, which ſhould be had in precious account and eſtimation for their workes ſake, euen as the veſſels of Gold and ſiluer in the Lords temple, and as the Angels of the Lord of hoſts) are baſelie eſtéemed euen as if they were veſſelles of earth or wood. If this did reach onely vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men themſelues or vnto their diſgrace, it were the leſſe, and might with leſſe greefe bee borne: but the contempt and diſgrace reach in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the glorious Goſpel of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, becauſe in the diſgrace of the men, the power of their miniſtrye is weakened. For where the teacher is
<pb facs="tcp:150926:11"/> euill thought of and diſpiſed, the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude dooth not regarde his doctrine. This euill goeth deepe, and if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well of it together with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer which I haue mentioned, ye ſhall ſée that vpon our owne experience we may ſay, indéede beholde how euill and how vncomlie a thing it is, for brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be at enmitie &amp; diſcorde. Theſe euils doo highly diſpleaſe almighty God, and if they bee continued in without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, who is able to ſhew the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and calamities which in time will enſue and come vppon vs in this Land? The contempt of the Goſpell, and growing into Atheiſme thereby, will drawe downe infinite plagues and miſeries. For the righteous God will not alwaies ſuffer ſuch abuſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuenged. Then ſéeing vnity is ſo good, bringing ſo manie bleſſinges, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde ſo euill, drawing ſuch an heape of miſcheefes with it, the one as a nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of true life, is to bee ſought for and maintained by all Godlye Chriſtians, and the other is to bee eſchewed as a deadly peſtilence: and this is to be don of vs ſpéedely, becauſe diſſention is like the breaking out of waters, the longer
<pb facs="tcp:150926:12"/> it continueth, the wider is the breache made and ſo becommeth the more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulte, to bee recouered. This béeing confeſſed of all, for there is no man I thinke that will denie, but that it is a moſt neceſſarie thing in Gods Church and amonge brethren, to eſchewe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and to ſéeke vnitie: therefore let vs in the next place conſider and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how it is to be ſought: for let let it be that we both agree, it is to bee ſought, and alſo doe ſéeke for it, yet if we ſéeke not the right way, we are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the better for ſeeking. Firſt then knowe this, that there are two ſortes of vnity and agreement, the one is in God, being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, in the ſpirite, in true holines and ſanctification. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is in error and ſin and not in the Lord. Now indeede it is the holy vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the Lord, which is praiſed in this Pſalme, and which wee muſt ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vpon which the bleſſing of God ſhal come. This may ye ſée by that exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of S. <hi>Paul Epheſi.</hi> 4. When hee ſaith, ſtudying to keepe the vnity of the ſpirite in the band of peace, for he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth as the reaſon, there is one body, and one ſpirit, as ye are called in one
<pb facs="tcp:150926:12"/> hope of your calling: one Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and father of all, &amp;c. For like as all the members of the naturall body are coupled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by one ſoule and make but one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: ſo by one ſpirite of the Lord, all the faithfull are vnited, and become all one miſticall body of Ieſus Chriſt: by one faith, and by one baptiſme, they are all in one Lord, and in one God. The fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this vnity is in the truth, and by it men growe vp together in God: and for this cauſe it is ſayd in the firſt verſe of the Pſalme, <hi>Brethren alſo to dwell in vnitie:</hi> He ſayth (alſo) becauſe as there is a reconciliation wrought by Chriſt betweene God and man, and ſo a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is come into vnitie with God, he muſt alſo growe into vnity with thoſe which are together reconciled to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord with him: ſeeke this vnity, to be vnited with our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto God, otherwiſe, all ſhall bee diſſolued and ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in confuſion. Touching that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concorde which is in errour and wickednes, they which poſſeſſe it who are of diuers ſortes doo commend it, and much complaine of the diſturbaunce and breach thereof. As firſt of all the
<pb facs="tcp:150926:13"/> Papiſtes make a great exclamation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs which profeſſe the glorious Goſpell, and haue forſaken them: that like wicked Sciſmatickes, wee haue diſturbed and broken this holy vnitye, by rendinge our ſelues from the true Church, and ſo from the faith, and from Chriſts miſticall body: this is a grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and a ſore accuſation, if their vnity which they glory of, were in the truth. But ſéeing it is moſt euident that they haue forſaken the truth of God, blaſpheme and condemne it, and ſet vp abhominable errours and curſed Idolatrye, all their agreementes, all their holy league (as they terme it) is no more but a moſt wicked and curſed conſpiracie againſt God and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. What is their vnity more then that which is deſcribed by the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſalme. 2. Why doe the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles rage, and the people meditate that which is vaine? The Kings of the earth ſtand vp, and the Princes take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile together againſt the Lord, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Chriſt? Here is a great vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nay a conſpiracy of wicked traitors againſt Chriſt. This perplexitie is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled by them: And we haue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement
<pb facs="tcp:150926:13"/> of God by the voyce of the Angel, Come out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among them my people and ſeperate your ſelues: ſo that all their cry is nothing againſt vs, we haue not diſſolued this bleſſed vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty here commended, but haue forſaken their curſed conſpiracy, which the née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer a man is ioyned vnto, the further of he is from God. Let no man therefore be troubled or diſquieted by their great wordes, but forſaking them, imbrace the holy faith, and be vnited thereby to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Prophetes and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and all holy men, vnto Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Yee ſhall here many other ſortes of men complaine, that there is not fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and vnitye kepte with them. When indéede as they walk after their wicked and vncleane luſtes in all ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable ſinnes, as in contempte of Gods word, in drunkenneſſe, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, pride, ambition, couetouſnes, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, extortion, bribery, oppreſſion, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and many ſuch like. The holy ghoſt ſaith vnto vs, haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitefull workes of darkneſſe, but rather reprooue them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. We can not ioyne Chriſt and
<pb facs="tcp:150926:14"/> 
               <hi>Belial,</hi> we can not be vnited to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord and haue fellowſhip in wicked ſins: If we ſay we haue fellowſhip with him (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) &amp; walkein darkeneſſe, we lie, &amp;c. 1. <hi>Iohn. ver.</hi> 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11. He that crieth out for peace, and dooth walk in vngodly wayes, ſtraying from the truth and from ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he will ſéeme to be, he is naught elſe but a diſturber and breaker of all holy vnitye. For who can take parte with him in thoſe thinges, but he ſhall ſeperate him ſelfe (as I haue ſhewed) from trueth and Godlines, without which there can be no bleſſed vnity? S. <hi>Peter</hi> calleth our Lord Ieſus Chriſt a liuing ſtone, vnto whom all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full comming as liuing ſtones, are built vp and become a ſpirituall houſe. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. If ſtones be not ſquared and made ſmoothe to ſitte and ioyne togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, howe ſhall they growe into one buylding? If men bee not framed in fayth and godlines, how ſhall they be vnited in the Lord? In déede there bee imperfections both in doctrine and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, all the beſt hewen ſtones haue ſome ruggednes remaining, and men muſt beare one with an other in much:
<pb facs="tcp:150926:14"/> for charity muſt couer the multitude of ſinnes. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. while the Temple of God is in the world, the ſtones are not perfectly ſet together, but the work is ſtill in hand, this temple is ſtill in buylding, we muſt beware of the down fall on that ſide alſo. Then ſéeing this bleſſed vnity muſt bee in God, in the truth, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit, to be built vp in Chriſt Ieſus, in true ſanctification (for he that is in Chriſt is a new creature) and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all concorde without this founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhall fall downe as a rotten buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, let the holy booke of God be our ground, let it be brought foorth to cut downe all controuerſies, and let men if they looke for any part of the bleſſing here promiſed, yéelde all honor and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto this ſacred worde. Yea let no man ſtand vpon his owne honour or reputation: If he haue maintained any thing awrie, but ſo ſoone as euer he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpieth the trueth in any matter, yeelde thereunto, let the truth of God goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and lead vs the way. For this is the onlie way to growe into this holy vnitie. And let ſuch as walke awrie, forſake their euill wayes, imbrace the heauenly trueth, and followe the rules
<pb facs="tcp:150926:15"/> thereof, if they will be accounted ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of peace and concorde. Ioyning thus vnto the trueth, both in faith and godlines of life, we ſhall be ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Lord, and it ſhalbe ſaid, beholde howe good and how comely a thing it is, for brethren alſo to dwell at vnity. It ſhalbe like that precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the head of <hi>Aaron, &amp;c.</hi> The heauenly graces and giftes of the holy ghoſt, ſhall come downe vpon vs plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly and flowe vnto euerie mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: we ſhall bring foorth fruite vnto God watered with heauenly dewes: we ſhall haue that great and high bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God almightie vnto eternall life. Therfore if it be not too late, that the ſinnes of this land haue prouoked the Lord to diſpleaſure, let all men lift vp their hartes and cry vnto the Lord, that he will beſtowe this precious iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell vpon vs, that wee may be at vnity (not in al manner of wicked vices, nor in errors) but in the Lord. And nowe who ſhall ſéeke this vnity? who ſhall ſtudie to aduance it? This may be in queſtion. I anſwer, euen all ſtates and degrees of men, priuate perſons, rulers and teachers, euen all and euery one
<pb facs="tcp:150926:15"/> that will looke for any part of Gods bleſſing muſt aduance it: Euery man I ſay muſt looke vnto the heauenlye truth of the holy religion, and imbrace the ſame with all loue and harty affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Euery man ought to bee zealous in ſpirite of the glory for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For if a man haue not the zeale of religion, hee cannot bee a good man, whether he be ruler or priuate man, though he ſéeme to be neuer ſo peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſaith to the Angell of the Church of <hi>Laodicea, Reu.</hi> 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art neither hot nor colde, I will ſpew thée out of my mouth: God dooth reiecte all ſuch dull and drowſie Atheiſtes, and irreligious perſons, which are ſo earthly minded, as that they regarde not the heauenly graces which are offered in the Goſpell. Let all men therefore ſtirre vp their harts to be feruent in gods truth, and let not Godlie zeale be quenched. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> further (as I haue alſo ſhewed before) wee muſt ioyne the practiſe of this holye word, as the Apoſtle <hi>S. Iames</hi> willeth, be doers of the word &amp; not hearers one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, deceiuing your ſelues. <hi>Ia.</hi> 2. <hi>ve.</hi> 19. for the great diſturbance of peace and
<pb facs="tcp:150926:16"/> the greeuous breaches of vnity, and all bitter diſſentions do chéefely ariſe from hence, that all ſorts &amp; degrees of men do not walk in the rules which God hath preſcribed vnto them in his word. We muſt therefore enter more particularly into this matter, that wee may ſée how each man is to further this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnity. I beginne with the priuate perſon, for whom there are rules pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in Gods word for him to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, if he wilbe a true member of the Church, and a ſéeker and preſeruer of this vnity, and ſo a partaker of Gods bleſſing vnto life euerlaſting. One rule is touching ſubiection &amp; reuerence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to rulers and gouernous, both Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall: for God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to honour and obey them. Submitte your ſelues vnto all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ordinaunce of man, for the Lordes ſake: whether it be vnto the king, as vnto the ſuperior, or vnto gouernours, as vnto them that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of euill doers, and for the praiſe of them that doo well. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 13.14. Alſo of this obedience and ſubiection for conſcience ſake, of this reuerence and honour to bee rendred,
<pb facs="tcp:150926:16"/> S. <hi>Paule</hi> writeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.2.3.4.5.6.7. Likewiſe obey them that haue the ouerſight of you and ſubmit your ſelues, for they watch for your ſoules as they that muſt giue accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. The neglect &amp; breach of this rule, euen the denying of obedience, reuerence, and honour vnto the rulers, gouernours and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, diſturbeth &amp; ouerthroweth the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which is here praiſed. If then a man wil not make conſcience to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this duty in obeying the holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the lord, what is he other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an enemy vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true concord, a diſſoluer of vnity &amp; peace? But what if rulers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, Paſtors &amp; gouernours faile, and come ſhort in ſome duties, and thereby ſéeme vnworthy to be regarded? I ſay if they do, they ſhal anſwer before God for it, but yet priuate men are not ſet at liberty, they are not diſcharged from this obedience &amp; rendring honour vnto them: for it is vnto the authority, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods ordinance that they do it, and not in reſpect of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. God hath not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the duties of men which are to be don vnto others, vnder this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if they performe all that which
<pb facs="tcp:150926:17"/> they ought to doo on their partes, or if they be ſuch manner of men as they ought to be. But he hath preſcribed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans duty abſolutly. If an other faile in his, he ſhall anſwer (as I ſaid) for it before God, thou haſt no warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hereby to depart from the rule which God hath ſet vnto thée. For thou art ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in conſcience vnto God to obey his will, &amp; not in regard of man, or of thine own benefit to do this or that: for by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed Apoſtle, we ſée that chriſtian ſubiects, &amp; faithful ſeruantes, are commanded euen for conſcience, to giue honor vnto heathen Princes, and infidel Maiſters. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. we muſt then from this expreſſe word of God obſerue, that when gouernours do amiſſe, men haue not their tongues ſet at libertie to reuile, and to reproch them, or to diſhonour them with euill ſpeech: ſéeing it is alſo writen, Thou ſhalt not curſſe the ruler of the people. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. <hi>ver.</hi> 28. But contrariwiſe, prayers, and ſupplications are to bee made vnto God, for rulers and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Lords people. When they offend, it is with great hurt to the Church, and therefore men are to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:150926:17"/> and mourne for it, and not to make themſelues mery with ieſtes and reproches. Let all euill ſpéeches of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace then be turned into prayers, and the laughter into teares, for this ſhall be more pleaſing vnto God. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beare him ſelfe in hand, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the breach of holy concorde, when he obſerueth not the rules of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, of ſubmiſſion, of reuerence and honour to be giuen vnto gouernours.</p>
            <p>Another rule is giuen by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, in theſe wordes: That ye ſtudie to be quiet, and to meddle with your owne buſineſſe, and to worke with your owne handes, &amp;c. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.11. as God hath diſtributed vnto euerie man, and as the Lord hath called euerie one (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſo let him walke, and ſo ordaine I in al churches. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. God hath ordained the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall places and callings, hee hath giuen gifts of abilitie to men to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the thinges he requireth in the ſame, he hath alſo ſet the boundes and limits within which euerie one is to keepe himſelfe, and to walke orderly, medling with that which appertaineth vnto him. This is an holy thing and
<pb facs="tcp:150926:18"/> comely, a preſeruer of vnitie: But it is much broken, and great euil enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thereof: for there be many priuate perſons, which would ſeeme verie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and to ſeeke the holy vnitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue others, which leaue the dueties of their places and callings, and buſie themſelues wholy with thoſe matters which do not belong vnto them. For as if the matters of their trades and ſciences were too baſe, or as if the care of their familie were a thing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vilde, they ſet theſe aſide, and neglect them: and take vpon them greater and higher buſineſſe. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding anye thing amiſſe in the Church, as if God had ſet them to bee ouerſeers of the gouernours and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, contrarie vnto this rule of <hi>S. Paule,</hi> they labour not with their handes, nor meddle quietly with their owne buſineſſe, but they bend all the powers of their minde, to diſpute and reaſon about gouernment, and the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of gouernours and teachers, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring about, and ſéeking to perſwade and draw others to their minde. They thinke thus to doe GOD high ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: But who hath giuen them
<pb facs="tcp:150926:18"/> power to diſpenſe with this rule, that yee ſtudie to bee quiet, and to meddle with your owne buſineſſe, and to labour with your handes? Hath God called them and ſet them aworke about greater thinges, and freed them from theſe? Is it not the ordinance and will of our God, that men ſhall inſtruct and guide their families in his waies?</p>
            <p>Is there not labour and paines and care to be taken, that the children and ſeruants may learne the holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and walke in it? But there are many which deepely meddle in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like matters, and if they haue two or three children and as many ſeruants, they are left ignorant, no paines taken about them, they may walke awry many waies, the care thereof is little. Alſo a mans owne matters which <hi>S. Paule</hi> willeth to meddle with, are in prouiding earthly thinges, neceſſarie for his familie: ſo that <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith, if there be any that prouideth not for his owne, namely for them of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, he denyeth the faith, &amp; is worſe then an infidel. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. and ſo in other dueties. Shall wee thinke the
<pb facs="tcp:150926:19"/> truth is obeyed, or that God is pleaſed by ſuch waies? when the rulers and guides of Gods people doe amiſſe, a man is to ſorrow at it, he is to looke to his way that hee kéepe vpright before God: but when in reprehending that which others fault in, hee neglectteth his owne calling, how ſhall he eſchew this ſentence, thou art therefore inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable (O man) whoſoeuer thou art that iudgeſt another, for in that thou iudgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelfe. For thou doeſt the ſame thinges that thou iudgeſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. Thou leaueſt vndone thy duetie in guiding that ſmall charge committed vnto thee. And let vs make the compariſon, is he not more worthie blame that fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fault with the greater, and doth it not in the leſſer, when the greater is more difficult to be performed? It is harder to gouerne a whole kingdom, a citie, or a flocke, then a little family, and more faultes will appeare. How vnreaſonable a thing then is it that a man which guideth not his little fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in any ſuch order as God requireth, ſhould let goe the ſight of his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and wholy giue him ſelfe in
<pb facs="tcp:150926:19"/> ſpéech to depraue the publike guides. Lament and ſorrow for euil, conſent notthereunto in any wiſe, follow the waies of the Lord, obey the rules of the word: and therefore let all men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde this, and keepe their place and ſtanding which God hath ſet them in, and ſo walk as that they may anſwer before the highe Iudge, and giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count howe they haue diſcharged their duetie.</p>
            <p>To come now to the gouernours and guides of the Lordes people: and firſt to the paſtors and ſhepeheards which haue the power and authoritie Eccleſiaſticall. Theſe are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, and aboue all other, and after a ſpeciall ſorte to procure, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue this bleſſed vnitie, as the end for which they are giuen of Chriſt, doth ſhew. He hath (ſaith <hi>S. Paule</hi>) giuen ſome to be Apoſtles, &amp; ſome Prophets, ſome Euangeliſts, ſome Paſtors and teachers: and then he ſheweth to what end, ſaying, for the repairing of ſaints, for the worke of the miniſtrie, &amp; for the edification of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt: till we al méet together in the vnitie of faith, and that acknowledging of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God,
<pb facs="tcp:150926:20"/> vnto a perfect man, &amp; vnto the meaſure of the age of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fulnes of Chriſt, &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 11.12.13. This is their whole worke &amp; labour appointed them, euen to build vp Chriſtes body, the Temple of God, by framing &amp; cupling together the liuing ſtones, vnto that vnitie of brethren, which is commended in this Pſalme. Then let vs ſée the rules pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in gods word, which they muſt obſerue to performe this holy worke, the elders (ſaith <hi>S. Peter</hi>) that are amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you, I beſéech, which am alſo an Elder and a witnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſufferings of Chriſt, and alſo a partaker of the glory that ſhall be reuealed, féed the flocke of God which dependeth vpon you, caring for it not by conſtraint, but willingly: not for filthie lucre, but of a ready minde: not as though ye were Lordes ouer Gods heritage, but that ye may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to the flocke. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>Firſt the ſhéep of Chriſt are to haue food, their life dependeth therupon. It is required therefore in all ſhepeheards that wil anſwere their calling before God, to haue the ſame affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them which Chriſt had: who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw the multitude he had compaſſion on them,
<pb facs="tcp:150926:20"/> becauſe they were as ſhéepe without a ſhepeheard. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 36. pittie &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion vpon the ſtraying ſhéepe muſt moue them to féed: yea loue muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine: For Chriſt ſaith to <hi>Peter, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ioanna</hi> loueſt thou me more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe? feede my ſheepe: loueſt thou me? féede my lambes: loueſt thou me? feede my ſhéepe: as if he ſhould ſay, of al loue do this for me. Here I am to moue thoſe which bee in authoritie in the Church, if it may any waie come to their eares, I do humbly beſeech them for the Lorde Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, to haue compaſſion vpon the flocke, that the ſheepe may haue their appointed food, euen the bread of life plentifully broken vnto them, that they may bee led into the greene paſtures, and vnto the fountaines and ſtreames of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing waters: cry alſo vnto the Lord of the harueſt, that he will poure downe his ſpirit vpon them, that in compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there may be labourers ſent forth: And that ſuch as haue taken vpon them the charge, and be idle or abſent, may be compelled to doe their duetie: that ſuch as be not able to féed, or that walke in a diſſolute and wicked beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb facs="tcp:150926:21"/> in life and conuerſation, may be remoued: And that ſuch as bee both ſkilfull to teach, and of godly life may be ſet ouer them, to guide them both by doctrine and enſample. If this be not performed, howe is the true concorde and vnity ſought? If the people be not inſtructed and led in the way of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: how ſhal they be framed and built together in one holy temple? If the Shepheard bee vngodly and giue cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt example: what peace, what v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or what agréement can ſuch as will feare God, hold with him? And if there be a diuiſion betwéene the ſhéepe and the Shepheard, where ſhalbe the vnity of brethren? It is out of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie that the meane to worke the Godly vnitye of brethren, is, that the flocke of Chriſt be fedde and guided by ſkilfull Godly men, which teach doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and giue good enſample in life and conuerſation.</p>
            <p>And now touching the care of the flocke, not by conſtraint nor for gaine, but willingly and of a ready minde: not as Lords ouer Gods heritage, but as enſamples to the flocke. I doo againe inſtantly beſéeche the Paſtors and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerners
<pb facs="tcp:150926:21"/> euen for Chriſtes ſake, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound and to increaſe in all fatherly loue towards the Lords people, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which this care can not rightly bée performed. Followe herein the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſetting foorth his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and trauaile, not of ambition or deſire of gaine, nor with roughnes, but as he ſaith, we were gentle among you euen as a Nurſe cheriſheth her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. where this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue is broken of, there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth (to the exceeding decay and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church) that which the Lord complained of by the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel</hi> againſt the Paſtors of Iſraell. Woe be vnto the Shepheardes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> féede them ſelues: ſhould not the ſhepheards féede the flocks? Ye eate the fat, and ye cloth ye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wooll: ye kill them that are fed, but yée féede not the ſheep: the weak haue ye not ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: the ſick haue ye not healed, neither haue yee bound vp the broken, nor brought againe that which was driuen away: neither haue yee ſought that which was loſt, but with violence, and with cruelty haue ye ruled them. <hi>Eze.</hi> 34. <hi>ver.</hi> 2.3.4. This was the ſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:150926:22"/> the flocke then, and ſhalbe euen to the worldes ende: that among Chriſtes ſhéepe as ſome bee ſtrong, ſo ſome bee weake, ſome ſicke, ſome going aſtraie. Yea ſuch are the frailties of all the faithfull, ſo many are the errors and the ſinnes which doo breake foorth: but yet they are ſtill the ſheepe of Chriſt, the Iſraell of God, &amp; the Shepheardes of Iſraell are to looke to them. Now I ſay, if there bee not a fatherly loue in the Shepheards to couer the multitude of ſinnes: If there be not a tender com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, as in the Nurſe towards the little babe, in ſteede of care to heale the broken and ſicke, and to ſupporte the weake, to bring into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way that which ſtrayeth, they ſhall deſpiſe and loath them as not worthy to bee regarded, yea they ſhall with violence and rigor beate and bruſe them, certaine it is, that the greater the frailties are, the greater care and compaſſion is to bee ſhewed. So that violence and rigor are not fitte to be in the Sheepheardes. For ſhall the nurſe throw the little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fante againſt the ſtones, or puſh it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde when it can hardlie ſtande a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? Shall the Sheepheard take his
<pb facs="tcp:150926:22"/> ſtaffe and ſtrike the young and tender Lambes? Or ſhall hee beate and bruſe the weake &amp; féeble ſhéepe? What ſhall we ſay, are the ſhéepe of Chriſt of leſſe valew? Many of them are weake and feeble in knowledge, many of them are but as young babes, as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall power of ſanctification. A num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſinnes do breake from them. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are wounded in conſcience &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in ſpirit: here is place for the loue, the care, the compaſſion and labour of Sheepheards. O ye ſheepheards of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell put on this loue and compaſſion, loath not the ſheepe of Chriſt for theſe frailties, rule them not with violence &amp; cruelty: but féede and ſupport, and heale them with all méeknes and long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Let no peruerſnes or iniuries of any of the ſhéepe towardes the ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, breake of the courſe of this loue and care. For if they looke vnto this, how the ſheepe deſpiſe them, howe they walke ſtubbornely againſt them, they ſhall neuer bee able with patience and méekenes to go through w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worke. If we thinke it an vnworthy thing, or ſuch as dooth diſcharge the ſheepeheard from his tender loue and care, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may
<pb facs="tcp:150926:23"/> warrant him to be rigorous, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſheepe do not reuerence him. Looke vpon <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> two great &amp; notable ſeruants of God, two ſpeciall ſheepeheards of the Lords flocke, who is worthy to be compared with them? They haue lefte an example to bee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. How great thinges did <hi>Moſes</hi> for the people? And yet how often did they murmur againſt him, &amp; were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſtone him? How many were their rebellions and iniuries don vnto him? And yet his loue is not quenched, his care dooth not faile, but his praier is moſt earneſt vnto God to pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them: He ſtill eſtéemeth them (though not al) as the Lords choſen people. What can they do more vnto vs, then goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſtone vs? Behold alſo the excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding aboundant loue of <hi>Paul,</hi> who wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed him ſelfe accurſed from Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his kinſemen the Iewes which were obſtinate might be ſaued. How much greater was his loue to the faithful of his kindred? And yet could they, euen the Church of Ieruſalem ſcarce thinke any thing wel of him all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but thought hardly of him, though he did neuer ſo much for them? This is
<pb facs="tcp:150926:23"/> gathered by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he writeth, <hi>Ro.</hi> 15 where he firſt ſheweth that it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them of <hi>Macedonia</hi> and <hi>Achaia</hi> to giue ſomewhat to the poore Saints in Ieruſalem, and that he went with this their beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſee it deliuered: and then he intreated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be very earneſt in praier to God for him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might be deliuered from the diſobedience of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> and that his miniſtry towards Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem might be accepted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints. It is a merueilous thing to conſider, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there being ſo great néede in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church at Ieruſalem, and that money being ſo welcome to thoſe which are in penury, and he carying ſo plentifull ſtore, yet there needeth earneſt praiers that this his ſeruice might be accepted. He had mooued the Curches of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentiles, (as appeareth in his ſecond Epiſtle to the Corinthians) to make this liberal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution. He wrought this matter, he goeth vp with it, ſo great was his care. Yet when he ſheweth all this loue and diligence towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how great was their miſliking of him, that hee feareth his miniſtry would not bee acceptable to them? The cauſe of the miſliking, <hi>Iames</hi> dooth ſhew vnto him when hee
<pb facs="tcp:150926:24"/> was come vp, <hi>Act.</hi> 21. <hi>ver.</hi> 21. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it was reported he had taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes among the Gentiles to departe from <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; not to circumciſe their children. We ſée he loueth them deere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for all this, and calleth them ſaints: Notwithſtanding their great frailtie in this matter, and the harde opinion they conceiued and held of him, ſo great &amp; ſo worthy a ſeruant of the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. What a patterne of méeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; fatherly loue is here for al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes of the Lords flocke to followe, among the poore feeble and wandring ſheepe, which doo not ſo reuerence and regard them as they ought to doo. The ſheepheardes as S. <hi>Peter</hi> requireth, muſt be examples to the flockes, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of all other are to ſhew meekenes, long ſuffering, and that loue which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the multitude of ſins: where the paſtors abound in this fathely loue, &amp; do not fall vpon the fraile ſheepe &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der lambes with rigour and violence, the bleſſed vnitie of brethren here prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is cheefely furthered: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> building vp of Chriſtes body in ſanctification is greatly aduanced, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of the paſtors &amp; teachers. The multitude are
<pb facs="tcp:150926:24"/> drawen thereby to imbrace &amp; to follow the truth. I do therfore again humbly beſeech all the paſtors and guides of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to conſider of this holy rule and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy examples and to practiſe it, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord may be brought into true concord and brotherly amity. Then laſtly, it appertaineth alſo vnto rulers in ciuill matters to maintaine this vnity according to the truth. They are to miniſter iuſtice &amp; true iudgement vnto all, to puniſh the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill doers, and to cheriſh and maintaine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good. Mercy and loue is alſo neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in them, that they may deale euen as fathers when they correct and chaſtiſe. If this be not, there will great miſcheefes enſue, euen to the diſturbance of all godly peace and concorde: for let a ruler, a iudge, or a mighty man be voide of religion, and withall giuen to anger, dealing among the Lords weake and feeble ſheepe, he will be ready to beate them downe and to cruſhe them in peeces. The frailties and ſinnes are many that breake foorth euen from ſome of Chriſts ſheepe and lambes (as we ſee, there be the weake, the ſicke, the bruſed and ſuch as erre) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing is odious in them, becauſe they profeſſe holineſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot in them be borne: therfore lift
<pb facs="tcp:150926:25"/> vp your harts in earneſt prayer vnto God, that he will powre downe the ſpirite of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue and mercy vpon rulers and iudges, that they may deale in the Lordes flocke, and towardes his poore weake ſheepe, with ſuch regard as that they may anſwer before Chriſt. Thus if we honour and imbrace the trueth, if we practiſe the rules thereof, euery one performing thoſe duties which the Lord inioyneth, the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and iudges, paſtors and gouerners in the Church, as alſo the priuate perſons, we ſhall growe into this holy vnity which the holy Ghoſt here praiſeth, we ſhall receiue all heauenly gifts and bleſſings, yea euen that great bleſſing of all bleſſinges, the life for euermore. Graunt this vnto vs O Lord, for thy deare ſonnes ſake our redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer &amp; Sauiour: to whom with thee &amp; the holy ghoſt three perſons, and one euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God, whom we worſhip, be all honor, glorie, dominion and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150926:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
